RAJA CHAUDHARY

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

raja@rajachaudhary.com
https://www.rajachaudhary.com/
Toronto, Canada

SUMMARY

Full Stack Developer with over 6 years of experience specializing in backend development with **Python** and **Java**, and frontend development experience with **Vue.js** and **HTMX**. My expertise spans a wide range of technologies, including **AWS** services, web hosting, and **containerization**. I excel in **communication**, ensuring effective **collaboration** with team members and stakeholders. My **problem-solving** abilities and adaptability allow me to navigate complex technical challenges and evolving project requirements with ease.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer | HP (Hewlett Packard)

2022-03-14

Working for HP under HCLTech, a global IT service provider with over \$13 billion in annual revenue.

- Collaboratively architected and led the development of SpringBoot microservice middleware for Microsoft product buyers on the client's payments dashboard processing invoices worth more than \$50 millions each month
- Worked closely with senior architects and leads to ensure seamless integration of the middleware with multiple downstream payment services of HP
- Managed and executed North American deployments, ensuring scalability, and successfully planned for future expansions
- Directed the implementation of a rate limiter feature leading a team of 4, effectively reducing API call losses by more than 90%
- Enhanced system performance by 15% through the strategic optimization of REST endpoint integrations with microservices
- Spearheaded the integration of Amazon Kinesis, boosting data throughput and system responsiveness by 20%
- Achieved a 50% reduction in defect resolution time through advanced system monitoring and proactive API failure/retry management
- Enforced DRY and SOLID principles, maintaining 90%+ unit test coverage, which resulted in clean, reusable, and flexible code architecture

Web Developer | Freelance

2021-11-08 - 2022-02-25

Delivered a complete full-stack website with backend built on Django and front-end built with HTMX and Daisy UI.

- Led the development of a comprehensive full-stack website for a rehabilitation clinic with seamless payment processing and subscription management
- Dynamic page rendering with HTMX and beautiful components built with Tailwind CSS
- Designed administrative features for content control and an enhanced user experience
- Implemented Redis/Celery Beat message queues for automated client reminder emails, boosting user engagement

Web Developer | GR Marketing

2020-03-23 - 2021-08-06

Senior developer at a web and marketing agency.

- Oversaw project delivery for 5+ web applications, ensuring seamless execution requirements gathering, development and delivery
- Engineered responsive websites using Vue.js and Tailwind CSS, prioritizing user-friendly interfaces
- Led the development of a Django based robust e-commerce website, incorporating key features like user authentication, cart functionality, session management, and a secure payment gateway.
- Integrated third-party applications like Google Maps, Mailchimp, and Stripe, enhancing website functionality
- Orchestrated cloud deployment on Heroku, Digital Ocean, and Amazon AWS for scalability and reliability
- Mentored and lead a team of 3 junior developers, fostering collaboration and knowledge-sharing

Software Developer | Petdom

2015-04-13 - 2017-08-11

A comprehensive solution for all pet requirements, Petdom served as a virtual umbrella offering homes and shelter to abandoned dogs

- Co-led backend initiatives, architecting and implementing Django and Postgres infrastructure. Result: a cohesive & user friendly pet platform
- Employed advanced search algorithms, achieving 90%+ accuracy in providing targeted, localized views of available dogs for adoption
- Integrated secure online purchasing, generating 500,000+ INR in quarterly revenues from a centralized marketplace for pet accessories

• Enhanced utility by integrating a user-friendly booking system for pet owners seeking veterinary care

Research Analyst | Grail Research (Integreon Solutions)

2012-06-26 - 2015-03-06

- Worked on more than 15 primary research projects to conduct market analysis
- Created complex VBA macros for automated data cleaning and presentation tasks enhancing efficiency
- Conducted cohort, segmentation and regression analysis with 95%+ confidence for clients in diverse industries

PROJECTS

Portfolio

https://www.rajachaudhary.com/

- Portfolio website built with VueJS utilizing vuetify for handcrafted Vue components built with Material CSS
- Continuous Integration and Continuous Delivery pipeline built on Heroku

Polar Pulse

https://polarpulse.streamlit.app/

Al powered news app to get the latest Canadian news in less than 100 words

- OpenAl's dev api to allow ChatGPT generate summary for each news article
- Utilized FastAPI to fetch the latest news and BeautifulSoup to scrape news articles for fetching content
- Streamlit python framework to generate easy to host frontend web application

DuDap (Dig Up Da Past)

https://github.com/raja-chaudhary/duDap

DuDap was developed to centralize and manage relationship-related details in one location. The objective is to avoid losing pertinent information from the past, ensuring a comprehensive record for effective communication and decision-making

- Incorporated agile methodology to build a relationship management tool to keep track of all the important aspects of a relationship
- Google OAuth signup/login: added functionality for email verification and password reset
- Tracking all the arguments, promises, important dates, good or bad traits, lies, and romance with reminder emails
- Statistics: compare if you are having more arguments or having more physical intimacy with your partner

EDUCATION

Post Degree Diploma - Marketing | Camosun College, Victoria 2018-01-02 - 2019-06-18

Bachelor's of Engineering - Instrumentation and Control Engineering | University of Delhi, New Delhi 2008-08-08 - 2012-05-05

SKILLS AND COMPETENCIES

Programming Language and Frameworks: Python, Java, JavaScript, Django, FastAPI, Flask, Streamlit, SpringBoot, Vue, JQuery, AJAX, HTMX, Pytest, JUnit, Mockito | Tools, Platform and DevOps: Git, GitHub, SQL, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Tomcat, NGINX, Maven, Dockers, Kubernetes, Redis, ASW SNS/SQS, S3 Buckets, Kinesis, Lambda, Heroku, RabbitMQ, Celery, REST APIs, Splunk, Swagger, JIRA, ADO | Methodologies and Concepts: Agile, Data Structures and Algorithms

SOCIAL NETWORKS

LinkedIn

https://www.linkedin.com/in/raja-chaudhary

Portfolio

https://www.rajachaudhary.com

Github

https://github.com/raja-chaudhary